<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>MakeMyResume Guide</title>
    <link href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in" />
    <updated>2021-08-07T15:37:36+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>MakeMyResume</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://guide.makemyresume.co.in</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Can I Put Self-Employed on Resume?</title>
        <author>
            <name>MakeMyResume</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/self-employed-resume/"/>
        <id>https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/self-employed-resume/</id>
            <category term="Resume"/>

        <updated>2021-08-07T15:37:36+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/59/photo-1592151450113-bdf5982da1691" alt="Self-Employed on Resume" />
                    Yes, you should - though not verbatim. The term self-employment itself is generally associated with slacking off after quitting/being fired, or simply as a filler for resume gaps. You see, recruiters care about the skill sets you possess, and in certain cases, how well you&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/59/photo-1592151450113-bdf5982da1691" alt="Self-Employed on Resume" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Yes, </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">you should</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> - though not verbatim. The term self-employment itself is generally associated with slacking off after quitting/being fired, or simply as a filler for resume gaps.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You see, recruiters care about the skill sets you possess, and in certain cases, how well you fit with the company. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">They want someone who can hit the ground running, rather than investing a lot of time, effort, and money to train them for an uncertain reward. Someone who gets the job done, preferably exceptionally.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">What they don’t really care about is WHERE you gained the requisite skills. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For those of you at Google, Amazon, Apple, or other prestigious organizations that are irate at reading this, calm down. If you’re from such elite organizations with renowned work cultures, it helps gain brownie points. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Barring that, unless the recruiter has personal experience with any company you’ve worked in, it just does not matter.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">So how do you put self-employed on your resume?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Simple, really. Put in the </span><strong>actual job title</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Don’t write self-employed, freelancer, etc. These titles are vague, generic &amp; nondescript, and have a slight negative bias attached to them.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Of the two examples below, which seems more appropriate for a content role?</span></p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="2">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/59/gallery/image1.png" data-size="791x1024"><img loading="lazy" src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/59/gallery/image1-thumbnail.png" alt="" width="768" height="994"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/59/gallery/image2.png" data-size="800x1035"><img loading="lazy" src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/59/gallery/image2-thumbnail.png" alt="" width="768" height="994"></a></figure>
</div></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The former, right? Despite both having essentially the same meanings, the one on the left (especially at first glance) seems more apt, fitting &amp; diverse!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Another tip is to put in the exact same job title as the role you’re applying to! Whether it is content writer, copywriter, content creator, social media management, or some allied field, if you’ve done that work, you can tweak the title - you’re the only verifiable source. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Add words like contract, freelancer, consultant, etc. </span><strong>at the end</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to denote the capacity in which you worked, rather than the phrase ‘self-employed’.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">What should you provide in the work experience?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Frankly, structure it like any other stint where you were employed - that is to say mention all the tasks you performed, any key highlights or accomplishments&lt;link to ‘How do you write an impact on a resume?’&gt;, </span><a href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/resume-writing-tips/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">your skills and projects</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here’s a simple checklist to follow, chronologically:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Job title </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">- The same as the role you’re applying to, IF APPLICABLE; otherwise, go for the nearest applicable one. Avoid using self-employed and go for alternatives like contract, freelancer, consultant, etc.</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li aria-level="1"><strong>Duration</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> - Mention the duration in a </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mon YYYY - Mon YYYY </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">format</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li aria-level="1"><strong>Company </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">- IF you did create your own company/website/pages, use the name, even if it failed. Entrepreneurial spirit and the set of skills such as self-motivation &amp; discipline that come with it don’t go unnoticed</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Responsibilities </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">- Structure the sentences in the same way as an employed stint - include all the relevant and allied tasks performed, tools &amp; skills utilized and projects worked on. Remember to:</span>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="2"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Provide quantified information as it lends </span><a href="https://talent.works/2018/01/08/the-science-of-the-job-search-part-i-13-data-backed-ways-to-win/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">credibility</span></a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li aria-level="2"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mention the companies you worked for/with as a freelancer - take advantage of the smallest chance of network effects</span></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Highlights </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">- Ensure to mention notable work or accomplishments during your stint as a freelancer</span></li>
</ul>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why should you add freelancer/self-employed on your resume?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Doing so gives you a way to explain gaps in employment when you were not working as an employee. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Believe it or not, it can also HELP in ways that are especially relevant with the paradigm shift in professional life that the pandemic has caused - work from home. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Understandably, freelancers are far more accustomed to this sea change than the average employee in terms of both skills, as well as work ethic (and discipline). </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Organizations thus would want to hire them more than ever as they have demonstrated self-management skills preventing any drop in productivity as well.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lastly, it gives you the flexibility to customize and title yourself as you see fit - a boon for getting a 100% match to every role you apply for by simply tweaking your title to that of the position itself.</span></p>
<p><strong>TL;DR - </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">Yes, you should write about stints in a self-employment capacity. Just avoid using that term and use the actual job/work title with alternatives like contract, freelancer and consultant in the end. Structure the rest like you would a salaried position. Ensure to provide quantifiable information and achievements, and customize it to make it relevant to positions you;re applying to.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How Do You Write Impact On A Resume?</title>
        <author>
            <name>MakeMyResume</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/how-do-you-write-impact-on-a-resume/"/>
        <id>https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/how-do-you-write-impact-on-a-resume/</id>
            <category term="Resume"/>

        <updated>2021-08-02T21:17:43+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/58/photo-1543357480-c60d40007a3f1" alt="Resume Impact" />
                    You were probably in the midst of drafting your resume and suddenly realized you wanted to figure out how to mention a major professional accomplishment, right? Well, it’s good that you did! More than your general roles and responsibilities, it’s the impact you’ve created that&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/58/photo-1543357480-c60d40007a3f1" alt="Resume Impact" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You were probably in the midst of drafting your resume and suddenly realized you wanted to figure out how to mention a major professional accomplishment, right? Well, it’s good that you did! </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">More than your general roles and responsibilities, it’s the impact you’ve created that recruiters want to know - it separates you from a run-of-the-mill employee and provides a glimpse of your true capabilities. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Thus, it is vital to include any major impact/accomplishments you’ve had during your work experience.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Use the PAR framework</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So how exactly do you showcase your professional achievements? Simple - use the </span><a href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/resume-accomplishments/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">PAR framework</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> - a simple tool we designed at </span><a href="https://makemyresume.co.in/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">MakeMyResume</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to effectively demonstrate professional impact on the customer’s resume.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The PAR framework consists of 3 chronological elements, that answer the 3 main questions - Why, How &amp; What:</span></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Problem </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">- The WHY; the issue or area of improvement you solved/worked on</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Action </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">- The HOW; the corrective steps you took or the tasks you did to bring about the impact</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Result </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">- The WHAT; explaining the outcome of your efforts </span></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The ‘Problem’ section essentially contains the reason that spurred you to take action. It could be anything. Let’s take 2 examples:</span></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Something simple such as wanting to improve average customer satisfaction scores</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Something complex like overly long processes resulting in operational inefficiency </span></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The ‘Action’ section focuses on the efforts undertaken to solve the problems. In the case of the two examples, it could be:</span></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Adding a single line in a customer service trainee manual by asking customer care executives to start with a question as to whether the person they were speaking to had time to talk</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Removing redundant processes, upskilling employees to use the latest tools &amp; automating simple, but time-consuming processes</span></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The ‘Result’ section outlines the effect your actions had on the problem - how it mitigated it or resulted in an improvement. For our two examples, it could be on the lines of</span></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Improved CSAT scores to 93% from 69%</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Increased operational efficiency by 57% by consolidating various feedback &amp; quality check rounds into a single structured meeting and automating data entry</span></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Thus, the final output for these two examples would be something like this:</span></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Refined the customer service manual by making vital changes in the script, thereby improving CSAT scores to 93% from 79%</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Reduced process time and increased operational efficiency by 57% by consolidating various feedback &amp; quality check rounds into a single structured meeting and automating data entry </span></li>
</ol>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Points to keep in mind</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You might have noticed a few similarities in the final outputs above, intended to maximize the influence your impact has on the recruiter. These are:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Quantify your statement - it provides credibility to your point. If you don’t have the numbers on hand, calculate them. It can provide a </span><a href="https://talent.works/2018/01/08/the-science-of-the-job-search-part-i-13-data-backed-ways-to-win/"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">40%</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> boost</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to your hireability!</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Brevity is key - Provide the details within a single sentence, up to 3 lines; the longer your point, the faster recruiters lose interest in reading it</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Create a separate bucket under the work experience for the point(s) - this ensures they’re not skipped over during a perfunctory glance of your resume</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Following these pointers ensures your resume leaves a lasting impression on the recruiter and elevates it over the competition. Happy (job) hunting!</span></p>
<p><strong>TL;DR - </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">Use the PAR framework to make your achievements impactful. Underline the problem, highlight the actions taken &amp; demonstrate the result. Ensure that the resulting sentence contains quantifiable information and is no longer than a single sentence that is three lines long. Preferably include these points in a separate bucket under the same work experience!</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>What Do You Think Is The Most Important Part Of A Resume?</title>
        <author>
            <name>MakeMyResume</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/most-important-part-resume/"/>
        <id>https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/most-important-part-resume/</id>
            <category term="Resume"/>

        <updated>2021-08-02T21:17:29+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/57/pexels-photo-38320331.jpeg" alt="Most Important Part of Resume" />
                    Without a doubt, the Professional Summary. The professional summary is a holistic but concise snapshot of your profile, comprising three main aspects: Keep in mind, all of these (barring extracurriculars, should you choose to mention them) need to be geared towards the role you’re applying&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/57/pexels-photo-38320331.jpeg" alt="Most Important Part of Resume" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Without a doubt, the Professional Summary.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The professional summary is a holistic but concise snapshot of </span><strong>your profile</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, comprising three main aspects:</span></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Your experience (and outstanding achievements)</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> - Refers to the domain, sector, organization, roles, etc. you’ve worked in/managed, as well as any extraordinary accomplishments within them, if applicable.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Your skills </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">- Refers to the skills you possess and have developed over the course of your professional experience to excel at your workplace. Includes both soft and hard skills.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Your USP</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> - Refers to your key strengths, including your professional areas of expertise. You can also include extracurriculars such as volunteering, or developed non-professional skills such as stand-up, music, etc.</span></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Keep in mind, all of these (barring extracurriculars, should you choose to mention them) need to be geared towards the role you’re applying to - the summary is meant to portray you as the ideal candidate for </span><strong>that role</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, not the ideal worker in general. Thus, relevancy is the key aspect to remember while drafting any resume.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It requires the ability to identify cross-functional skills that can be applied to or are common across even drastically different domains.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For example, let’s say you’ve worked for a few months as a software engineer and want to switch to Marketing. They’re two widely different profiles - however, many skills (especially soft skills) overlap. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As both a software engineer and a marketing executive, you need to excel at understanding client requirements to deliver a product (be it an app or a campaign) to ensure utility and client satisfaction. Thus, interfacing with a client and understanding their requirements is a simple and basic, but vital skill applied to both domains</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As a software engineer, let’s also assume that you were able to identify additional applications of your app in a completely different segment. This demonstrates the ability to identify new channels for generating revenue - a crucial skill for a marketer as well!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We’re often asked by our customers if they have a chance at landing an interview when applying for a job in a completely different domain. Clearly, the answer is a resounding YES! It’s vital to identify HOW to market yourself and your skills in a way that the recruiter is able to firmly establish a pertinent link between the role and your profile, without resorting to blatant lies.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why is the Professional Summary the most important part of the resume?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Your Professional Summary is chronologically the first section of your resume containing details applicable to the role you’re applying for, and thus the first thing a recruiters’ eyes will fall on and scan through intently. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Its primary purpose is to ensure that the reader finds your profile relevant enough to the position applied to, to bother scanning the rest of your resume. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Thus, if your summary isn’t strong or relevant enough, your application will join the other rejects on the discard pile.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Apart from relevance, it also requires powerful content. No matter how relevant your profile, </span><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/forbeshumanresourcescouncil/2018/07/11/when-hiring-executives-top-recruiters-look-for-these-important-traits/?sh=57b5619d68a2"><span style="font-weight: 400;">recruiters are also looking for leaders</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. They’re (more often than not) employing you for the long-term, and want to ensure you have the ability to do so. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Accordingly, your resume must reflect this ability with the usage of action verbs, leadership skills, and quantified information, along with any exceptional accomplishments (awards, honours, statistics, etc.) to lend weight and credence to your application.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">How do we write a resume summary?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">To craft an effective and powerful professional summary, you must focus on 3 aspects:</span></p>
<ul>
<li aria-level="1"><strong>Length</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> - Your summary in its entirety should be a minimum of 3 points, and should not exceed 5 sentences/points. Additionally, each point should not be more than 3 lines long! This ensures that they read through the whole point rather than finding it too tedious to peruse.</span></li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Language </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">- Ensure that the summary is written using </span><a href="https://talent.works/2018/01/08/the-science-of-the-job-search-part-i-13-data-backed-ways-to-win/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">powerful action verbs and include leadership words</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, for a massive boost in hireability of up to </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">140%</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. It (obviously) needs to be free of any grammatical errors as well.</span></li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li aria-level="1"><strong>Content</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> - Quantified information is indispensable - it lends credibility and demonstrates the calculable impact that you’ve created.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Understandably, considering the sheer details, technicality and scope just a single section of a resume contains can be overwhelming, especially if you’re creating your resume from scratch. This is where professional resume writing services come through to ensure that no step or technicality is missed out, and our guide&lt;link to “Should I pay someone to write my resume?”&gt; can help you identify the best services out there for the same!</span></p>
<p><strong>TL;DR</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> - The most important part of a resume is the professional (or resume) summary. It serves as a snapshot of your profile, and essentially functions as your USP - only if your summary is powerful and relevant will recruiters read the rest of your resume. To ensure the same, it should be 3-5 points (no more than 3 lines each), should include action verbs &amp; leadership words, and quantified content. It must contain the relevant experience, skills, achievements and strengths you possess.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Is It Ok To Have a Two Page Resume?</title>
        <author>
            <name>MakeMyResume</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/two-page-resume/"/>
        <id>https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/two-page-resume/</id>
            <category term="Resume"/>

        <updated>2021-07-19T19:27:23+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/56/photo-1565688534245-05d6b5be184a1" alt="Two Page Resume" />
                    Ok? A two-pager is in fact the IDEAL length for a resume. (subject to certain criteria, which we’ll get to in a few). There are two main factors by which resume length is dictated, a sort of front-end &amp; back-end deal. On the front-end, we&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/56/photo-1565688534245-05d6b5be184a1" alt="Two Page Resume" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ok? A two-pager is in fact the IDEAL length for a resume. (subject to certain criteria, which we’ll get to in a few).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are two main factors by which resume length is dictated, a sort of front-end &amp; back-end deal. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On the front-end, we have work experience - yours, to be precise. Depending on whether you’re a fresher or newbie in the industry (upto 5 years of work experience), an industry veteran (5-10 years of work experience) or a leader (11+ years of work experience), your resume will range from 1 page to 3 pages.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For a fresher/newbie, the ideal length is 1 full page. It must neither fall short of nor exceed this limit. Unless you’ve quite literally had the roles and responsibilities of an entire department or organization dumped upon you (which, let’s face it, has rarely if ever happened to anyone barring head honchos of startups).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For a veteran, the resume should be up to 2 pages long. This is enough to capture the skills and work experience you’ve managed to obtain, without ending up too wordy.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lastly, for an extremely senior/leadership role, the widely-recognized upper limit for a resume is 3 pages, meant to provide enough space to detail your most valuable accomplishments and relatively recent work experience - <a href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/how-far-back-should-a-resume-go/">your resume should not go too far back</a>.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/number-pages-resume/">Our detailed guide</a> explains the reasons for these limits.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The back-end of this limit is attributed to the amount of time recruiters spend on reading your resume, ranging from 6-30 seconds during the initial filtering processes. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The longer your resume, the more tedious it feels to read and the lesser time and attention you get per page - the recruiters could end up missing out on key information which could have landed you that interview!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Thus, unless you belong to the criteria of:</span></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Not being experienced enough, or </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Belonging to offbeat sectors like teaching, science, etc., </span></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Always ensure your resume is 2 pages long!</span></p>
<p><strong>TL;DR - </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">A 2-page resume is the ideal length for a resume, especially if you have more than 4-5 years of experience. If it’s less, unless your profile is extraordinary, keep it to one page!</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How Many Pages Should A Resume Be?</title>
        <author>
            <name>MakeMyResume</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/number-pages-resume/"/>
        <id>https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/number-pages-resume/</id>
            <category term="Resume"/>

        <updated>2021-07-19T17:52:23+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/55/photo-1532153975070-2e9ab71f1b141" alt="Number of pages in a resume" />
                    How many pages is a resume? A resume should be two to three pages long, generally. While there are exceptions to this rule, it is widely recognized that they should never exceed this limit unless specifically asked to. That said, the length of a resume&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/55/photo-1532153975070-2e9ab71f1b141" alt="Number of pages in a resume" />
                <h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">How many pages is a resume?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A resume should be two to three pages long, generally. While there are exceptions to this rule, it is widely recognized that they should never exceed this limit unless specifically asked to.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">That said, the length of a resume is primarily dictated by the level of experience you possess, which can be categorized into 3 major brackets:</span></p>
<ul>
<li aria-level="1"><strong>0-5 years of experience - 1 page resume</strong><strong><br></strong></li>
<li aria-level="1"><strong>6-10 years of experience - 2 page resume</strong><strong><br></strong></li>
<li aria-level="1"><strong>11+ years of experience - 2/3 page resume</strong></li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>0-5 years of experience - 1 page resume</strong></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As a fresher or entry-level executive, you have neither a wealth of experience nor a long list of skills and professional achievements. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Extracurricular achievements and side projects, which make up the bulk of your resume, serve as differentiators at best; hence, they need not be listed in detail. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Only as you approach 4-5 years of experience does your resume warrant even the thought of expanding to more than a page. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">That too if you’ve managed to handle multiple roles within the organization(s) and had an extraordinary amount of work and responsibility handed over to you.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span></p>
<h3><strong>6-10 years of experience - 2 page resume</strong><strong><br></strong></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With an increase in seniority, your resume can extend to upto 2 pages. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">By now, you would’ve gained plenty of work experience and managed several roles and responsibilities. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Since these will be relatively fresh and recent, they can be explicated in detail to provide a better understanding of the variety of skills you have developed and knowledge you have obtained after working in your domain. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you belong to this category, you can apply to senior technical and entry- or mid-managerial positions, both of which require a diverse set of competencies, and your resume needs to be detailed enough to reflect that!</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span></p>
<h3><strong>11+ years of experience - 2/3 page resume</strong><strong><br></strong></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you fall under this bracket, you’re officially a veteran of the industry. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The myriad roles and responsibilities you’ve managed need a resume that’s a minimum of 2 pages, and could easily exceed it too. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">To effectively demonstrate your extensive professional expertise and wide repertoire of technical, managerial and interpersonal skills, a 2-pager is a must. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you have 15-20+ years of experience, and are aiming for a very senior or CXO-level position, a three-pager would be recommended as your resume will undergo extensive screening. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Recruiters will try to gauge not just your fit for the role, but the company as a whole too! Keep in mind, however, the fact that your <a href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/how-far-back-should-a-resume-go/">resume should not go back more than 15-20 years</a>.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why is resume length restricted?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There is no hard-and-fast rule that one cannot have a 5 or even 10 page resume; these restrictions are essentially tips based on research that has been proven several times - crisp resumes upto 3 pages long have the highest chance of being selected. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In fact, </span><a href="https://talent.works/2018/12/05/the-science-of-the-job-search-part-viii-your-chances-of-an-interview-plummet-if-your-resume-is-too-long/" rel="nofollow"><span style="font-weight: 400;">this research</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> analyzed 6000+ applications to identify the sweet spot for the word count - resumes ranging from 475 to 600 words had the highest chances of landing an interview. In certain fields such as in business, they found that long resumes (exceeding 600 words) were </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">72%</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> less hireable than those in the sweet spot. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Furthermore, a </span><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/brettnelson/2012/06/04/do-you-read-fast-enough-to-be-successful/?sh=64a20e18462e" rel="nofollow"><span style="font-weight: 400;">quick glance</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> reveals that “successful” adults read at 250-300 words per minute. When you take into account that the average time spent perusing a resume maxes out at </span><a href="https://jobs.theguardian.com/article/does-your-cv-pass-the-30-second-speed-test-/" rel="nofollow"><span style="font-weight: 400;">30 seconds</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, it effectively means recruiters read a maximum of roughly 125-150 words of your resume during initial screenings; it also means that 125-150 words are all you have to impress them. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Additionally, they scan </span><a href="https://www.ere.net/why-you-cant-get-a-job-recruiting-explained-by-the-numbers/" rel="nofollow"><span style="font-weight: 400;">4 main categories</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">:</span></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Job titles</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Companies you worked at</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Start/end dates </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Education</span></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Thus, deep-diving into any other sections is redundant. It seems the less is more adage applies to resumes too - as long as you don’t miss out on the important and relevant info.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Are there any exceptions to this rule?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">if you’re an academic or industrial scientist, college professor, school teacher, or social service worker you’re probably wondering how you could possibly fit all your work and/or publications within such a short resume. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fear not, this rule doesn’t apply to you! In fact, in these professions a longer resume is a sign of success - the more patents, research papers, charitable drives, etc. you have done, the better, and each needs to be documented for appraisal.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>TL;DR</strong> - The ideal resume is up to two to three pages long. The length is determined by your experience level - for those with 0-5 years work ex, 1 page is enough. For those with 6-10 years of work ex, a two-pager suffices. Only those with work ex of 10+ years should go for a three-pager. However, if you’re in the science, education or social service sectors, the longer your resume, the better.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How Far Back Should A Resume Go? </title>
        <author>
            <name>MakeMyResume</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/how-far-back-should-a-resume-go/"/>
        <id>https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/how-far-back-should-a-resume-go/</id>
            <category term="Resume"/>

        <updated>2021-07-09T14:37:36+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/54/photo-1506784365847-bbad939e93351" alt="How far back should a resume go" />
                    Your resume should go back 15 to 20 years, at most. It boils down to three major reasons: According to TalentWorks’ research, your hireability drops by 8% annually after you cross the age of 35. Recruiters guess your age using your graduation details, and your&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/54/photo-1506784365847-bbad939e93351" alt="How far back should a resume go" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Your resume should go back 15 to 20 years, </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">at most</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Why just 15-20 years?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It boils down to three major reasons:</span></p>
<h3>Hireability</h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">According to </span><a href="https://talent.works/2018/01/08/the-science-of-the-job-search-part-i-13-data-backed-ways-to-win/" rel="nofollow"><span style="font-weight: 400;">TalentWorks’ research</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, your hireability drops by 8% annually after you cross the age of 35. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Recruiters guess your age using your graduation details, and your hireability in their eyes could fall if you’re above the ‘age limit’.</span></p>
<h3><strong>Resume Length</strong></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you’re an industry veteran with a wealth of experience, expounding upon it, especially older stints and achievements, can prove detrimental. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Your resume could easily exceed 3 pages, the (widely recognized) upper limit for resume length. Unless you’re an academic, scientist or teacher/professor, resumes longer than 3 pages reduce your chances of getting an interview.</span></p>
<h3><strong>Relevancy</strong></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The further back your resume goes, the less relevant it becomes to the role you’re applying to. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">The skill sets, expertise, technical functions &amp; duties differ so significantly that what you’ve learned and executed back then would have little to no impact on your profile and knowledge base today. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Thus, a short, crisp and relevant resume trumps an excessively lengthy one any day of the week!</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Could you explain further?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sure! </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Recruiters want young blood in their organizations for fresher perspectives and contemporary knowledge of industry trends &amp; skill sets. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For example, let’s say you’re 40, and graduated 20 years back. After 10 years of work ex, you decided to change your field, and are now applying for a very senior position at a unicorn. Since it is 2021 now, your resume mentions your graduation date as 2001. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Using this, they can infer that you’re roughly in the 38-43 bracket (considering the length of courses, early/late schooling, etc.), and your chances of being hired compared to say a 30ish-year-old who graduated in 2011, fall automatically. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Thus, if your resume is restricted to your work experience of the last 15 years, they cannot accurately guess your age as being 35+ (though to be honest, it’s an easy calculation, but then they do not spend that much time during the first few rounds of resume filtering).</span></p>
<p><a href="https://jobs.theguardian.com/article/does-your-cv-pass-the-30-second-speed-test-/" rel="nofollow"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Recruiters spend roughly 6-30 seconds</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> scanning your resume during the initial resume screening processes. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">The longer your content, the lesser time they spend per page - do you really want them to miss out on important content because your resume was too long? </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Keeping your resume to a manageable 2 pages (3 at most, if you’re applying for a CXO-level position) ensures it’s packed with information &amp; important details while excluding irrelevant and unimportant snippets.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Step into the shoes of a recruiter that is hiring someone for a senior management position at an MNC. It requires leadership, foresight, vast knowledge of macro &amp; micro trends in the industry, excellent people-management &amp; negotiation skills. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Would the kind of work a potential candidate did at an intern- or entry-level position 25 years back have the slightest importance or relevancy in terms of the knowledge or experience required for the position? Obviously not! </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Consequently, either completely eliminating or only very briefly mentioning these is the preferred practice and norm, especially since it helps in reducing the length of your resume and even gives you more space to highlight recent and more relevant experience and achievements which could go a long way towards getting you that interview.</span></p>
<p><strong>TL;DR</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Your resume should go back no more than 15-20 years from the time of applying to a role. It helps the resume be of a manageable length, reduces the chance of an age bias working against you, and provides a much more relevant and informative resume!</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>2021 Job Search - Definitive Action Plan</title>
        <author>
            <name>MakeMyResume</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/job-search-action-plan/"/>
        <id>https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/job-search-action-plan/</id>
            <category term="Job Search"/>

        <updated>2021-07-06T21:06:08+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/53/job-search-plan_e2hyi3-2.jpg" alt="Job Search Action Plan" />
                    <p>A job search can be quite tedious most of the times. However, if you plan the job search well - you'll figure that you're much at ease with the job application process. Not every Job Search process will lead you the right kind of job. However, if you have taken enough time to plan the process out, you are surely headed the right way. According to a journal article in the <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1879403?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents" rel="nofollow">Economics of Information and Job Search</a>,  in a labor market characterized by uncertainty, both employers and employees are searching. A <a href="https://talent.works/blog" rel="nofollow">survey</a> states that, despite some challenges in the market, the fact is there’s a pretty significant increase in jobs available now than in previous years — over 200% in certain industries<em>.</em></p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/53/job-search-plan_e2hyi3-2.jpg" alt="Job Search Action Plan" />
                <p>A job search can be quite tedious most of the times. However, if you plan the job search well - you'll figure that you're much at ease with the job application process. Not every Job Search process will lead you the right kind of job. However, if you have taken enough time to plan the process out, you are surely headed the right way. According to a journal article in the <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1879403?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents" rel="nofollow">Economics of Information and Job Search</a>,  in a labor market characterized by uncertainty, both employers and employees are searching. A <a href="https://talent.works/blog" rel="nofollow">survey</a> states that, despite some challenges in the market, the fact is there’s a pretty significant increase in jobs available now than in previous years — over 200% in certain industries<em>.</em></p>

<p>Just follow the simple steps to a Definite Action Plan for your Job Search</p>
<h2>Know your strengths and weaknesses</h2>
<p>This point is crucial, not just before planning a job search, but also until you land an interview with any organization. One must be able to identify their strengths and weaknesses at the earlier stage. If your strength lies in excellent communication - you know you'd easily fit into roles like PR, Sales, Trainer. Moreover, identifying your weaknesses before a job search can buy you enough time to build on those weaknesses and convert them into strengths.</p>
<h2>Start your initial search</h2>
<p>What exactly would an initial search include? Do you know how to look up jobs on a job portal? Are you well informed about the various jobs that exist on job portals? Are you aware of the right keywords you can use to get the right jobs? One needs to be thorough with the initial homework. An initial homework would include the use of the right keywords, knowledge of the various job portals along with the job postings.</p>
<p>Moreover, have you studied the market well for the field you've chosen? Do you know the designation that exists for the type of job you're seeking? Hence, an initial search is crucial. It's a virtual peek into the market. Also, it is done to get you familiarised with the type of jobs that exist in the market. Moreover, you get introduced to job descriptions, which state the roles and responsibilities of the candidate an employer is seeking. Don't mess up your initial search, take time out and do it well!</p>
<h2>Revamp your resume</h2>
<p>Your resume is your ticket to land a good job. It's simple, if the details on your ticket aren't precise and accurate, you don't get past the boarding gate.  Similarly, your resume needs to state every detail precisely. Do you still hold an outdated resume? Well, then it's time you revamp it.</p>
<p>If you still think, you can fake a few details on your resume to put up an impressive document - you're wrong. Every detail put on your resume must hold evidence. Update your recent <a href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/resume-certifications/">certifications</a>, <a href="https://makemyresume.co.in/blog/2018/11/resume-education/">educational qualifications</a>, <a href="https://makemyresume.co.in/blog/2018/11/volunteer-experience-resume/">volunteer experience</a>, and your previous <a href="https://makemyresume.co.in/blog/2018/11/resume-work-experience/">work experience</a>. Make sure your resume looks fresh.</p>
<h2>Create a target list of companies</h2>
<p>We all have that dream list of companies we want to work for. Now is the time you start carving your dream to reality. If you have envisioned working for a particular company, now is the time to make your dreams more realistic. Create a list of companies and make a target list. Put Google to the best use and research about those companies. This extends your knowledge concerning the organization you're targeting, and when you land an interview with the same organization - you're best placed to answer any questions the interviewer throws at you regarding the organization.</p>
<p>Don't let the interviewer have an impression that you haven't done your homework well. Knowing about the organization you wish to work for will always give you an edge over the other applicants.</p>
<h2>Create your online presence (LinkedIn)</h2>
<p>What does a platform like LinkedIn do? Do you think it enhances your job search? Well, LinkedIn is one of the most widely known platforms to explore your job opportunities. LinkedIn connects you to different employers around the globe, where you have the opportunity to explore your choices. If you intend to get noticed by the well-known employers on LinkedIn, it is really important to create an online presence before you venture into the application process.</p>
<p>Take time out and build your LinkedIn profile. LinkedIn provides you with various sections, where the right amount of information can get you to the right employer. Increase your reach, so when recruiters look up your profile, they aren't spending time browsing - Your profile is out there among the top searches! LinkedIn also provides you with a section to look out for jobs. All you do is enter your preferred designation, for eg: Manager with your preferred location. Do you see how creating an online presence can multiply your chances of getting closer to your dream job?</p>
<h2><strong>Network online</strong></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We cannot stress their enough - CONTACTS MATTER. By networking with like-minded individuals, especially if they belong to the same domain, you can demonstrate your capability and competency. Thus, should a vacancy arise in their organization, your network contacts could notify you of the same, and if thoroughly impressed with what they’ve seen of you, potentially even vouch for you, helping you land a more senior role at a better organization. </span><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/power-your-professional-vouch-ronnie-battista/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">This article</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> explains the power of a professional ‘vouch’ and the impact it can have on your job prospects!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are various ways and forums you can network professionally, LinkedIn being foremost. To a smaller extent, Facebook and Twitter too can be used for the same. You can even network via popular community forums like Reddit, Pinterest, Quora, etc. Engaging with &amp; producing content of your own via blogs, podcasts, articles, etc. too helps!</span></p>
<h2><strong>Strengthen your Profile</strong></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Recruiters today look for more than just academic or professional achievements - they want productive individuals that contribute not just to the organization, but to the society at large too. Employees function as the organizations’ ambassadors, and they want to ensure they’ve got the creme de la creme. Furthermore, they’re interested in hiring candidates that demonstrate a desire to learn and update themselves constantly. It also helps if you have personal extracurricular achievements.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The ideal candidate, thus, would be one with impressive academic (mainly if you’re a fresher) and/or professional achievements, with a few courses and tools under their belt used in the domain they’re applying to, who also actively pursues their hobbies and volunteers at the local NGO.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Take 2 candidates, A &amp; B. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A has 1 year of experience in Social Media Marketing, possesses know-how regarding various tools like Buffer, Quuu &amp; Canva, and recently did a course on Content Strategy from Coursera. A table tennis champ at the local club, they're a member of Sunday Friends and actively participates in at least 1 drive per month. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">B has 1 years’ experience in Social Media Marketing, and while their numbers seem as good as A’s, they has done no supplementary courses and they're  only heard of Canva &amp; Buffer, never used them. They've never even heard of Quuu. He spends most of their free time with friends at the local bar playing pool, or binging OTT content. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Despite B being just as competent as A, their profile reflects no upskilling. their knowledge and skillset will become outdated and obsolete soon. Conversely, A is constantly updating their skillset and knowledge base and demonstrated a drive to learn more. They've also contributed to their neighbourhood and people have a high opinion of them. Even though B has not spent their time nefariously, it offers the company no benefit as opposed to having A allied with them - A could contribute to their CSR activities, with the added benefit of having a conscientious individual linked to their brand.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Really want that job you’ve dreamed of? Be like A.</span></p>
<h2>Recap</h2>
<ul>
<li>Know your strengths and weaknesses</li>
<li>Start your initial search</li>
<li>Revamp your resume</li>
<li>Create a target list of companies</li>
<li>Create your online presence</li>
<li>Network online</li>
<li>Strengthen your profile</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Image Credit: Unsplash</em></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Five Tips To Ace That Zoom Job Interview</title>
        <author>
            <name>MakeMyResume</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/zoom-job-interview/"/>
        <id>https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/zoom-job-interview/</id>
            <category term="Interview Prep"/>

        <updated>2021-07-06T13:57:14+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-lg1.jpg" alt="Zoom Job Interview" />
                    <figure class="alignnone wp-image-779"><img loading="lazy"  title="Skype Job Interview" src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/skype-video-call_zdkjmy.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/responsive/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-xs.jpg 300w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/responsive/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-sm.jpg 480w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/responsive/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-md.jpg 768w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/responsive/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/responsive/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/responsive/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-2xl.jpg 1600w"  alt="Skype job Interview" width="1920" height="1281"></figure>
<p>In today’s time, most interviews are Zoom interviews. Companies do this for multiple reasons: the organization has its head office located in another country or another city. Sometimes, due to the candidate unavailability and the urgency to fill in the position, employers immediately conduct a Zoom job interview.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-lg1.jpg" alt="Zoom Job Interview" />
                <figure class="alignnone wp-image-779"><img loading="lazy"  title="Skype Job Interview" src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/skype-video-call_zdkjmy.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/responsive/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-xs.jpg 300w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/responsive/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-sm.jpg 480w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/responsive/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-md.jpg 768w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/responsive/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/responsive/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/39/responsive/skype-video-call_zdkjmy-2xl.jpg 1600w"  alt="Skype job Interview" width="1920" height="1281"></figure>
<p>In today’s time, most interviews are Zoom interviews. Companies do this for multiple reasons: the organization has its head office located in another country or another city. Sometimes, due to the candidate unavailability and the urgency to fill in the position, employers immediately conduct a Zoom job interview.</p>

<p>People form first impressions when you meet them in person. However, first impressions can be made rapidly through a Zoom job interview as well. Just to make sure, you are giving your best at the Zoom job interview, follow these quick tips:</p>
<h3>#1 Make sure you have an uninterrupted internet connectivity</h3>
<p>The first thing to do before the Zoom call is to check on your internet connectivity. You require a seamless internet connection. An interrupted Zoom interview can have a negative effect and break the link of the interview discussion. So make sure, your internet is connected well and is functioning at a good speed. Use Wi-fi connection instead of the mobile data, since the mobile data often gets interrupted.</p>
<h3>#2 Appropriately position your laptop or phone</h3>
<p>Remember, the Zoom job interview isn’t any casual video call with your friend. Thus, it is important to know that you need to set your mobile phone on a stable surface where you are visibly clear. Avoid holding your phone in your hand, since you will end up moving it multiple times and it comes across as highly unprofessional.</p>
<h3>#3 Use of wired/ wireless headphones</h3>
<p>During a Zoom job interview, don’t rely on the microphone to communicate. Any possible disruption of the voice and the background sounds can lead to disturbances during the ongoing interview. Get your headphones ready in advance before scheduling the Zoom job interview.</p>
<h3>#4 Non-Verbal Cues and Body Language</h3>
<p>A Zoom job interview is nearly similar to a personal interview. Your interviewer can easily capture your body language and <a href="https://makemyresume.co.in/blog/2017/10/decoding-non-verbal-cues-interview/">non-verbal cues</a> through the video. Sit upright, and dress in formal attire. Make sure you are not walking around any corridor during the interview. Treat this as important as equal to a personal interview.</p>
<h3>#5 Prepare and Request Feedback</h3>
<p>Prepare well in advance and take a test call a day in advance with a friend. Make all the necessary preparations concerning the equipment as well as to the questions you are likely to counter at the actual interview. You will receive a glimpse of the actual interview. Once you're done with the interview, request feedback from your friend and appropriately make improvements.</p>
<h2>Recap</h2>
<p>5 Tips to Ace That Zoom Job Interview</p>
<ul>
<li>Make sure you have uninterrupted internet connectivity</li>
<li>Appropriately position your laptop or phone</li>
<li>Use wired or wireless earphones</li>
<li>Non-verbal cues and body language</li>
<li>Prepare and request feedback</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Image Credit: Pixabay</em></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>5 Salary Negotiation Tips - Know How To Negotiate</title>
        <author>
            <name>MakeMyResume</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/salary-negotiation-tips/"/>
        <id>https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/salary-negotiation-tips/</id>
            <category term="Job Search"/>

        <updated>2021-07-06T13:55:30+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/302-1140x815_tftreu-lg1.jpg" alt="Salary Negotiation" />
                    <figure class="alignnone wp-image-785"><img loading="lazy"  title="Salary Negotiation" src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/302-1140x815_tftreu.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/responsive/302-1140x815_tftreu-xs.jpg 300w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/responsive/302-1140x815_tftreu-sm.jpg 480w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/responsive/302-1140x815_tftreu-md.jpg 768w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/responsive/302-1140x815_tftreu-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/responsive/302-1140x815_tftreu-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/responsive/302-1140x815_tftreu-2xl.jpg 1600w"  alt="Salary Negotiation" width="1140" height="815"></figure>
<p>Salary negotiations are one of the most difficult barriers to pass at the time of signing an offer with any organization. Think you’re offered too less? Will you come across as greedy, if you’re asking for a higher salary? How do you prove to the person across the table about your capabilities? Too many thoughts to battle against before actually getting to the negotiation. You have simple 5 negotiation tips to follow that could ease this process.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/302-1140x815_tftreu-lg1.jpg" alt="Salary Negotiation" />
                <figure class="alignnone wp-image-785"><img loading="lazy"  title="Salary Negotiation" src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/302-1140x815_tftreu.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/responsive/302-1140x815_tftreu-xs.jpg 300w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/responsive/302-1140x815_tftreu-sm.jpg 480w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/responsive/302-1140x815_tftreu-md.jpg 768w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/responsive/302-1140x815_tftreu-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/responsive/302-1140x815_tftreu-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/38/responsive/302-1140x815_tftreu-2xl.jpg 1600w"  alt="Salary Negotiation" width="1140" height="815"></figure>
<p>Salary negotiations are one of the most difficult barriers to pass at the time of signing an offer with any organization. Think you’re offered too less? Will you come across as greedy, if you’re asking for a higher salary? How do you prove to the person across the table about your capabilities? Too many thoughts to battle against before actually getting to the negotiation. You have simple 5 negotiation tips to follow that could ease this process.</p>

<h3>Understand benchmarking</h3>
<p>Your time is valuable and you don’t want to waste it on an organization that isn’t offering what you are worth. This requires you to understand how employees understand their salary levels and thus adjust your job search.</p>
<p>At the same time, Companies use various benchmarking tools. They compare average pay rates with:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pay at other companies in their industry</li>
<li>The salary for professionals with your level of education and experience</li>
<li>The income of professionals in your field in their area of the country</li>
</ul>
<p>Employers interested in you will offer you the best salary after weighing your competencies. However, understand the benchmarking process and make the right negotiation.</p>
<h3>Shift focus from past pay to future potential</h3>
<p>Your future pay package is usually always given in reference to your past pay. When you are at the table talking about your offer – the concerned HR person will give you a hike based on your previous salary. This is a normal process and most organizations follow this. Regardless, there are tactics you can use to have the hiring manager focus on what you can do now and in the future. Take his mind out of the past and let him know your goals and aspirations on the new job.</p>
<h3>Understand their constraints</h3>
<p>The organization may like you. They also think you deserve everything. However, when you look at the salary break-up – these intentions are not visible there. Why? You have to understand that every organization sets a budget for an employee. They have constraints and salary caps that no negotiations can break. In such a circumstance, your job is solely to figure out whether they are flexible or not. During a bulk selection, for e.g. Any organization taking in 20 people at the same time, your salary can’t be higher than the other. However, you would have noticed that your organization has been generous and flexible at the start dates, vacations, bonuses and additional incentives.</p>
<p>It’s better you understand the organization’s constraints before you put forth your proposal. Don’t make any decision without gauging all the problems.</p>
<h3>Everything counts</h3>
<p>Remember when you are calculating your salary – don’t get too excited on the whole figure. Usually, employees get happy at the whole figure and forget to calculate the components of the salary. Remember to consider the value of benefits like bonuses, commissions, health insurance, flexible spending accounts, profit-sharing, paid vacation, stock benefits. You have to take into account every component and then make a final proposal.</p>
<h3>Don’t get emotional – Get Creative</h3>
<p>Don’t be too focused and emotional about your salary while negotiating. You need to create a certain reputation which doesn’t come across and desperate and greedy. Instead, create a smart image – make the employer feel you have that spark in you, and they are convinced about giving you a higher salary.</p>
<p>Negotiations don’t need to focus only on the salary structure. Instead, try using creative ways and negotiate on the time period, especially if it’s a contract term. Use creative ways and negotiate on getting a contract of a year instead of 6 months. This can also change the perspective of the employer, and you may just notice your salary get better.</p>
<p>Remember, the more a company wants you, the more salary negotiation leverage you have.</p>
<h2>Recap</h2>
<p>5 Salary Negotiation Tips</p>
<ul>
<li>Understand benchmarking</li>
<li>Shift focus from past pay to future potential</li>
<li>Understand their constraints</li>
<li>Everything counts</li>
<li>Don’t get emotional - get creative</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Image: <a href="https://www.freepik.com/premium-photo/hand-businessman-giving-dollars-cash-money-to-hand-man-with-corruption-concept_2086480.htm#term=salary&amp;page=1&amp;position=6" rel="nofollow">Freepik</a></em></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Thank You Letters and Job Interviews</title>
        <author>
            <name>MakeMyResume</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/thank-you-letters-job-interviews/"/>
        <id>https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/thank-you-letters-job-interviews/</id>
            <category term="Letters"/>

        <updated>2021-07-06T13:54:02+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-lg1.jpg" alt="Thank You Job Interview" />
                    <figure class="alignnone wp-image-464"><img loading="lazy"  title="Thank You Letters" src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/responsive/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-xs.jpg 300w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/responsive/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-sm.jpg 480w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/responsive/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-md.jpg 768w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/responsive/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/responsive/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/responsive/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-2xl.jpg 1600w"  alt="Thank You Letters" width="4641" height="3094"></figure>
<p><strong>“Thank you”</strong>- It’s amazing how these two simple words that mean so much can seem so little. <strong>T</strong><strong>hank you letters</strong> or even a trivial message can go a long way in helping you show your appreciation. And with that come several perks, in addition to providing a boost to your career. In the words of Simon Mainwaring –</p>
<blockquote>“<em>The simple act of saying<strong> ‘thank you’</strong> is a demonstration of gratitude in response to an experience that was meaningful to a customer of citizen.”</em></blockquote>
<p>And going by that, it can be said that <strong>thank you letters</strong> can definitely help you cement a good relationship with clients, vendors or even in getting an eventual job offer. So, let us talk about <strong>thank you letters</strong> - more importantly, how they are of help in job interviews.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-lg1.jpg" alt="Thank You Job Interview" />
                <figure class="alignnone wp-image-464"><img loading="lazy"  title="Thank You Letters" src="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/responsive/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-xs.jpg 300w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/responsive/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-sm.jpg 480w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/responsive/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-md.jpg 768w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/responsive/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/responsive/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/media/posts/25/responsive/thank-you-letters_pim31m-1-2xl.jpg 1600w"  alt="Thank You Letters" width="4641" height="3094"></figure>
<p><strong>“Thank you”</strong>- It’s amazing how these two simple words that mean so much can seem so little. <strong>T</strong><strong>hank you letters</strong> or even a trivial message can go a long way in helping you show your appreciation. And with that come several perks, in addition to providing a boost to your career. In the words of Simon Mainwaring –</p>
<blockquote>“<em>The simple act of saying<strong> ‘thank you’</strong> is a demonstration of gratitude in response to an experience that was meaningful to a customer of citizen.”</em></blockquote>
<p>And going by that, it can be said that <strong>thank you letters</strong> can definitely help you cement a good relationship with clients, vendors or even in getting an eventual job offer. So, let us talk about <strong>thank you letters</strong> - more importantly, how they are of help in job interviews.</p>

<h3>Thank-you letters for job interviews</h3>
<p>One might ask- <em>"How do<strong> thank-you letters</strong> help in case of <a href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/selling-yourself-effectively-interview/">job interviews</a>?" </em>Well, to answer in a practical way, it is courteous to do that. It is actually important to say thank you to an employer after an interview - it helps to reiterate your views to the employers as to how the job interests you. More importantly, <strong>thank-you letters </strong>help to highlight you in a better light <em>(even if your <a href="https://guide.makemyresume.co.in/interview-doand039s-and-donand039ts/">interview did not go according to plan</a>)</em> and entrench your position as the best suitable candidate.</p>
<h3>How to write thank you letters - helpful tips</h3>
<p>Now that we know the importance of <strong>thank you letters</strong>, let's talk about how to write one in the first place.<strong> Thank you letters</strong> should help you thank everyone - from recruiters to everyone who assisted in your job search. Here are some basic points that you should keep in mind while writing <strong>thank you letters</strong> -</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Knowing who to address the thank you letters to</strong></li>
<li><strong>It is all about making an impact and standing out</strong></li>
<li><strong>Take measures to keep it short and simple</strong></li>
<li><strong>Proofread and spellcheck the thank you letter</strong></li>
<li><strong>Lastly, remember to actually write the words <em>"thank you"</em> </strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Writing <strong>thank you letters</strong> can oftentimes be the key to getting a job offer. In these days of email and online communication, taking the time out to thank your potential employers can <em>(more than anything else)</em> emphasize the fact that you are a well-mannered person. Other than that, it can also reinforce the fact that you want the job. Use your <strong>thank you letter</strong> to address any issues and concerns that came up during the interview. Try to discuss anything of importance that the interviewer might have neglected to ask. And while doing that, restate as to why you want the job, what your qualifications are, how you might be able to contribute positively towards the organisation.</p>
<p>So, the next time you apply for a job - remember to write a <strong>thank you letter</strong>. And as Alfred Painter had once mentioned -</p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>"Saying 'thank you' is more than good manners. It is good spirituality"</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/0YbeoQOX89k?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText" rel="nofollow">Hanny Naibaho</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/search/photos/thank-you?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText" rel="nofollow">Unsplash</a></em></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
